This year at CES, Intel brought its latest laptop processors.
Intel今年在CES上带来了最新的笔记本处理器
Intel’s 3rd-gen Core Ultra processors.
英特尔第三代酷睿Ultra处理器
Codenamed Panther Lake.
代号Panther Lake
This is the first new product you can buy that uses Intel’s 18A process.
这可是你能买到的首款使用Intel 18A工艺的新品
This processor’s performance will directly decide whether Intel’s process is
这颗处理器的表现直接决定着Intel的工艺是不是
truly Great Again.
的确Great Again
And its specs are also clearly different from Intel’s previous standard-power laptop processors.
而且它的规格也和以往的Intel标压笔记本处理器有明显的区别
Today we’ll use this Lenovo Xiaoxin Pro 16 GT AI Yuanqi Edition that packs it,
今天我们就用这台搭载着它的联想小新Pro 16 GT AI元启版
to take a good look at how this 18A flagship, which Intel is pinning big hopes on, really performs.
来好好看看这颗被Intel寄予厚望的18A当家花旦表现到底怎么样
How good is the efficiency?
能效好不好
Enough talk, let’s officially get started.
话不多说 咱们正式开始
In a previous episode, we already introduced the improvements to the 18A process.
我们在之前的节目里已经跟大家介绍过了18A工艺的改进
Simply put, it’s Intel’s first post-FinFET-era product.
简单地说它是Intel第一款后FinFET时代的产物
It’s Intel’s first GAA transistor process.
它是Intel首个GAA晶体管的工艺
And it also uses Intel’s PowerVia back-side power delivery technology.
再加上它还使用了Intel的PowerVia背面供电技术
So the efficiency of this new processor should be something to look forward to.
这颗新处理器的能效表现应该挺值得期待的
Next, come with me and take a look at Panther Lake’s specs.
接下来跟我一起来看看Panther Lake本身的规格吧
As Intel’s biggest laptop-side product for the next year,
作为Intel接下来一年最重磅的笔记本端新品
Panther Lake’s specs are quite different from before.
Panther Lake的规格可以说和以往有着较大的不同
For the CPU, in total core count,
CPU部分 总核心数量上
a full-spec Panther Lake is still 16 cores.
满血的Panther Lake依然是16颗核心
But it’s not the 6+8+2 layout of Arrow Lake and Meteor Lake.
但它并不同于Arrow Lake和Meteor Lake的6+8+2规格
This time the P-cores drop from 6 to 4.
这次的P核从原本的6个减少到了4个
And the E-core count stays at 8.
而E核数量维持8个
While the LPE cores go from 2 to 4.
而LPE核则从原来的2个变成了4个
Just looking at the spec changes, you’re definitely thinking,
光看规格上的变化你肯定要说了
isn’t this a step backward?
这不是开倒车了吗？
There are fewer P-cores.
P核都少了
If you think that, you’re wrong.
这么想你就错了
These LPE cores aren’t like the LPE cores in Arrow Lake or Meteor Lake.
这颗LPE核可不是Arrow Lake核Meteor Lake那种LPE核
The previous LPE cores were placed in the SoC Tile.
之前的LPE核心是放置在SoC Tile里的
In other words, they were separate from the main CPU.
换句话说就是它独立于主CPU之外
That meant they couldn’t access the CPU’s L3 cache and SLC cache at all.
这就造成了它根本没法访问CPU的L3缓存和SLC缓存
And even funnier,
更搞笑的是
almost no software could actually make use of those LPE cores.
以前的LPE核几乎没有软件能调用得了
You could say back then the LPE cores were like the Android camp’s A5xx.
可以说当时的LPE核就是安卓阵营里A5xx的定位
In my view they were basically useless.
在我看来是非常鸡肋的
What’s worse is,
更难受的是
Meteor Lake upgrading to Arrow Lake didn’t even change the SoC Tile,
因为Meteor Lake升级到Arrow Lake根本没换SoC Tile
so Arrow Lake basically inherited those two trash tiny cores.
相当于Arrow Lake这一代依然继承了这两颗废物超小核
You could say their most important contribution in Arrow Lake
可以说它们在Arrow Lake里最重要的贡献
was just two extra boxes in Task Manager.
可能就是任务管理器里多的两个框框了
But Panther Lake’s LPE cores this time aren’t that weak stuff.
但这次Panther Lake的LPE核可不是这种弱鸡货色
These new LPE cores are the same concept as the ones in Lunar Lake.
这颗新的LPE核和之前在Lunar Lake里的概念是一样的
They’re proper E-cores in another cluster.
它就是在另一个Cluster里的正经E核
They just don’t share the ring bus with the other cores.
只是不与其他核心共享环形总线
But performance is almost the same as the other eight E-cores.
但性能和其他的8个E核几乎是一样的
And they can access the SLC cache as well.
也同样能访问SLC缓存
They can also be scheduled and used normally like other cores.
也能像其他核心一样被正常调用
Their clocks aren’t low either.
频率也不低
With that,
这样一来
Panther Lake’s CPU side
Panther Lake的CPU部分
is split into a performance cluster made up of P-cores plus E-cores,
就分为了由P核+E核组成的性能簇
and an efficiency cluster made up of four LPE cores,
和由4个LPE组成的能效簇
a combination of two clusters in total.
总共两个Cluster的组合
This design is mainly for better battery life and efficiency,
之所以这样设计主要还是为了更好的续航表现和能效表现
because some light workloads can clearly be fully handled by today’s LPE cores.
毕竟一些轻载工作在如今的LPE核心上显然是可以充分胜任的
When they’re not needed, the performance cluster can save a lot of power.
性能簇在不需要的时候就可以省下不少的功耗了
This approach has already been fully validated on Lunar Lake.
这套方案在Lunar Lake上已经得到充分验证
I believe it will effectively boost Panther Lake laptops’ battery-life potential.
相信这会有效提升Panther Lake笔记本的续航潜力
We also tested the latency between the various cores.
我们也测试了它各个核心之间的延迟情况
You can clearly see a tri-cluster style.
可以看到很明显的三丛集风格
Latency between P-cores is in the 20–30 ns range.
P核之间的延迟在20-30ns的量级
Between P-cores and E-cores it’s around 40–50 ns.
P核和E核之间的延迟大约在40-50ns量级
Between E-cores it’s about 100 ns.
E核和E核之间的延迟大约100ns左右
Cross-cluster latency to the LPE cores is a bit higher,
LPE核跨簇的延迟会稍高
coming in at around 125 ns.
来到125ns左右
Overall, you can clearly see the latency differences between different cores.
整体来说你可以明显看到不同核心之间延迟的差别
Inter-core latency between E-cores is a bit higher than expected.
E核之间的核间延迟比预期高一点
Overall the latency is normal for a multi-cluster processor.
整体的延迟表现属于多Cluster处理器的正常水准
As for improvements to the CPU core architectures specifically,
而具体到CPU核心架构的改进上
it’s more about optimization,
它更多是以优化为主
rather than a completely new design from scratch.
而不是彻底全新设计的新核心
The Cougar Cove P-core architecture,
P核Cougar Cove架构
compared with the Lion Cove used in Arrow Lake and Lunar Lake,
相较于Arrow Lake和Lunar Lake使用的Lion Cove
improves branch prediction,
改进了分支预测能力
increases TLB capacity,
提升了TLB容量
and adds more capability for memory disambiguation,
以及增加了内存歧义消除的能力
with the goal of fully realizing Lion Cove’s IPC potential.
目的还是完全发挥出Lion Cove架构的IPC潜力
After all, even though Lion Cove made quite a few architectural changes,
毕竟Lion Cove在架构改进不小的情况下
the IPC uplift wasn’t as high as expected.
IPC提升并没有预期来得高
So Cougar Cove is here to raise the ceiling.
所以Cougar Cove就是来拉满上限的
The Darkmont architecture for the E-cores and LPE cores is also developed from the previous-gen Skymont.
E核和LPE核的Darkmont架构也是基于前代Skymont发展而来
Skymont left a deep impression on us last year.
Skymont架构在去年给我们留下了深刻的印象
As a small core,
作为小核
its same-clock performance was almost on par with Zen 4 and the Raptor Cove big cores.
它的同频性能几乎已经持平Zen4和Raptor Cove大核了
Darkmont continues to strengthen Skymont on that basis,
而Darkmont则是在Skymont的基础上继续增强
including branch prediction, dynamic prefetch control,
包括分支预测能力、动态预取控制
improved microcode throughput, and memory disambiguation capability.
增强的微码吞吐能力以及内存歧义消除的能力
Darkmont’s decoder clusters also go from 20b instruction-stream width to 24b.
Darkmont的解码器簇也由原先的20b指令流宽度提升至24b
Suppose I’m handling 8b-wide instructions,
假设我要处理8b宽度的指令
Each cluster’s instruction throughput used to be only 2 IPC.
那每个簇的指令吞吐之前只有2IPC
Now it’s 3 IPC per cluster.
现在就是每个簇3IPC了
Three decoders add up to 9 IPC.
三个解码器总共9IPC
For the already very wide Darkmont cores,
对于已经非常宽的Darkmont核心来说
in cases like this where a single instruction is relatively long,
像这种单个指令比较长的情况
it can significantly improve execution efficiency.
是可以显著提升运行效率
Panther Lake doesn’t just have major changes on the CPU side;
Panther Lake不仅在CPU部分有显著的变化
the off-core parts of the entire SoC change even more dramatically.
整颗SoC在核外部分的变化更是非常显著
One very important change is that
其中一个非常重要的变化就是
the memory controller has finally returned to the CPU’s Compute Tile.
内存控制器终于回到了CPU所在的Compute Tile
Do you know how big a difference this makes?
你知道这一点改变带来了多大的变化吗？
We measured the memory-access latency curves for each core,
我们测试了各核心下访问内存的延迟曲线
and you can see that
你可以看到
it’s still paired with LPDDR5X memory as well.
P同样是搭载LPDDR5x内存
On the ARL platform, latency at 128 MB depth reached 140 ns,
ARL平台在128M深度下的内存延迟来到了140ns
while on the PTL platform it drops straight to 100 ns!
与此同时你可以看到PTL平台的延迟直接降低到了100ns！
That gap is absolutely huge.
这个差距可以说是相当巨大
You have to remember that with Arrow Lake,
要知道Arrow Lake这一代
the main reason desktop gaming performance fell off a cliff
在桌面端游戏性能滑铁卢的主要原因
was the memory-latency hit from the off-die memory controller.
就是内存控制器外置所带来的内存延迟问题
Panther Lake clearly fixes a major issue from the previous generation.
Panther Lake无疑解决了一个前代存在的巨大问题
Another very important improvement comes from the GPU.
另一个非常重要的改进来自于GPU
First, Panther Lake’s iGPU moves to the brand-new Xe3 architecture
首先Panther Lake的核显换上了全新的Xe3架构
and supports XeSS 4× frame generation.
支持XeSS四倍帧生成
Depending on the spec positioning,
根据规格定位的不同
the currently announced Panther Lake processors include a CPU 4+0+4
目前发布的Panther Lake处理器包括CPU 4+0+4
paired with a low-power 4 Xe iGPU,
搭配4Xe核显的低功耗版本
a CPU 4+8+4 paired with a 4 Xe iGPU,
CPU 4+8+4搭配4Xe核显的版本
and a top-spec CPU 4+8+4 paired with a flagship 12 Xe iGPU.
以及CPU 4+8+4搭配12Xe旗舰核显的顶配版本
The SoC die paired with them is different as well,
与它们搭配的SoC Die也不同
so the number of PCIe lanes also differs.
因此PCIE通道数也不一样
But unlike the Compute Tile, which uses Intel’s own 18A process,
不过和Compute Tile使用Intel自家18A工艺不同
the 12 Xe GPU Tile uses TSMC’s N3E process,
12Xe版本的GPU Tile使用的是台积电N3E工艺
while the 4 Xe GPU uses Intel’s own Intel 3 process.
4Xe的GPU则是使用自家Intel 3工艺
Likewise,
同样的
the process nodes for the other parts are all different too.
其他部分的工艺也都各不相同
The IO Tile uses TSMC’s N6 process,
IO Tile的工艺使用的是台积电N6工艺
and the Base Tile that connects all the chiplets
连接所有芯粒的Base Tile
has also been upgraded from 22 nm to 14 nm.
也从之前的22nm工艺升级到了14nm工艺
So, we’ve quickly looked through Panther Lake’s technical changes;
咱们简单看完了Panther Lake在技术上的变化
now it’s time to get to today’s review star,
现在就该来了解一下今天咱们评测的主角
the 3rd-gen Intel Core Ultra X9 388H.
——第三代英特尔酷睿Ultra X9 388H了
Panther Lake’s naming rules have changed again compared to last gen.
Panther Lake这代的命名规则相比前代又有了一些变化
This time, models with the 12 Xe big iGPU all end in an 8.
这次搭载12Xe大核显的型号尾缀数字都为8
The three models using the full-fat 12 Xe B390 iGPU
使用满血12Xe B390核显的三款型号
have even changed their naming from Ultra 7 and Ultra 9 to
更是将命名从Ultra 7、Ultra 9改为了
Ultra X7 and X9 to reinforce the impression.
Ultra X7和X9来强化给人的印象
The Ultra X9 388H we tested this time
我们这次测试的Ultra X9 388H
is, across the entire Panther Lake lineup,
就是这代Panther Lake整个产品线里
the fullest-spec and highest-performance version.
规格最满、性能最强的版本
Its single-core boost clock is slightly lower than the previous 285H,
它的单核睿频比前代的285H稍微低一点
dropping from 5.4 to 5.1.
从5.4降到了5.1
Later in the performance tests we’ll also come back to single-core,
待会儿性能测试里我们也回来看看单核性能
to see whether it got stronger or weaker.
到底是变强了还是变弱了
The boost clocks for the E-cores and LPE-cores are similar,
E核和LPE核的Boost频率差不多
with the LPE cores a bit lower.
LPE核会稍微低一点
Under full all-core load, the P-cores can run at 4.8 GHz,
全核心满载时，P核可以跑到4.8GHz
while the E-cores and LPE-cores are both 3.6 GHz.
E核和LPE核则都是3.6GHz
On the memory side, it supports LPDDR5X-9600,
内存方面它支持LPDDR5X 9600内存
which should be quite important for the 12 Xe iGPU’s performance.
这对于12Xe核显的发挥应该是相当重要的
Next, it’s time to really put it to the test
接下来咱们就该来真刀真枪看看
and see how this Ultra X9 388H performs.
这颗Ultra X9 388H的性能表现了
For testing, we used Lenovo’s Xiaoxin Pro 16 GT AI Yuanqi Edition.
我们测试使用的是来自联想的小新Pro 16 GT AI元启版
This laptop uses a 16-inch 2.8K
这台笔记本采用了一块16英寸的2.8K
120 Hz, 1100-nit OLED display
120Hz、1100nits的OLED屏幕
and a huge 99.9 Wh battery.
搭载了99.9Wh的大电池
Inside, it uses a dual-heatpipe, dual-fan cooling module,
机内使用了一套双热管双风扇的散热模组
and for an iGPU-only model,
对于核显机型来说
this cooling setup can basically unleash its full potential.
这套散热基本上可以发挥出它应有的全部潜力
It’s very suitable as our launch test machine for the new Core Ultra generation.
非常适合我们作为全新一代酷睿Ultra的首发测试机型进行测试
First, let’s look at SPEC CPU 2017.
首先来看看SPEC CPU 2017的表现
Let’s start with the P-core results.
先来看看P核的表现
Even with lower clocks than the 285H,
388H的P核在比285H频率更低的情况下
the 388H actually scores higher.
成绩反而更高了
The big-core architectural changes are small,
大核的架构改进虽然很小
but you can indeed see IPC gains,
但IPC的确是可以看到提升的
about 10% in integer and about 7% in floating point.
整数10%左右，浮点7%左右
That’s a sizable uplift for an architecture without major changes.
这个提升幅度对于没有大改的架构来说不小了
The 388H’s E-cores and LPE-cores scored quite similarly,
388H的E核与LPE核则跑出了比较接近的成绩
because the core microarchitecture is exactly the same.
两者核心架构是完全相同的
What affects their performance is only frequency and cache configuration.
影响它们性能表现的只有频率和缓存配置
You can see that this generation’s LPE-core performance is not weak,
你可以看到这代LPE核的表现可并不弱
especially compared with the previous 285H’s LPE cores,
尤其是和前代285H的LPE一对比
the gap is simply enormous.
这个差距实在是太大了
E-core IPC has also improved further.
E核的IPC也得到了进一步的提升
Most absurdly, if they both run at 3.8 GHz,
最离谱的是如果同样跑在3.8GHz下
the new E-cores’ IPC is even roughly on par with last gen’s P-cores.
新的E核甚至IPC和前代的P核都差不多
And remember, this CPU has 12 such cores!
要知道这颗CPU里这样的核心有12个！
From the SPEC2017 results,
从SPEC2017的表现来看
Panther Lake’s P-core and E-core IPC both improve to some extent;
Panther Lake的P核和E核IPC都有一定提升
although peak frequency is slightly lower,
虽然峰值频率稍低
single-core performance hasn’t regressed.
但单核性能并没有退步
So how does the X9 388H perform in more tests?
那么X9 388H在更多测试里的表现怎样呢？
First, let’s look at the Cinebench series.
先来看看Cinebench系列的表现
This time we tested three generations: R23, 2024, and 2026.
这次我们测试了R23、2024和2026三代Cinebench的表现
You can see the 388H is slightly ahead of the previous 285H in both single-core and multi-core.
可以看到388H不论是单核还是多核成绩都稍强于285H
In the older R23, the advantage is a bit smaller.
在比较老的R23里优势会稍微小一点
HX370 is also slightly stronger than 388H in R23.
HX370也在R23里稍强于388H
Overall, the three CPUs’ multi-core performance is in the same tier.
三颗CPU的多核性能整体上是一个段位的水平
But during testing I noticed something interesting.
但测试的过程中我发现了一件有趣的事情
In high-load tests like Cinebench,
在Cinebench这样的高负载测试里
this X9 388H never hit the 80W PL1 power limit.
这颗X9 388H是没跑到80W的PL1功耗墙的
I thought it had run into some other limit,
我本以为是撞了其他墙
but on a closer look, it turns out the frequency was already maxed out at full all-core turbo.
仔细一看才发现原来频率已经完全跑满多核睿频了
In other words, its peak power was only 78W.
也就是说它的峰值功耗仅为78W
That’s a clear advantage compared to the previous 285H when it’s fully pushed.
这比起前代285H跑满时的功耗是有明显优势的
And that advantage shows up directly in efficiency.
这样的优势直接体现在了能效表现上
On the Cinebench 2024 efficiency curve,
在Cinebench 2024的能效曲线里
this X9 388H versus the previous 285H
这颗X9 388H比起前代的285H
shows a significant improvement.
有了显著的提升
Basically, at 45W,
基本上新U在45W时的时候
it’s already reaching what the previous gen needed around 70W to achieve.
成绩就已经来到了前代在70W左右的水平
That multi-core efficiency gain is obviously huge.
这个多核能效的提升显然是相当巨大的
If we compare it with HX370,
如果我们和HX370对比的话
you can see its efficiency is also slightly better than HX370’s.
可以看到它的能效表现也会稍微超过HX370一点
After all, HX370’s 12 Zen 5 cores
毕竟HX370的12颗Zen 5架构
with homogeneous big cores are still very strong in Cinebench.
同构大小核在Cinebench里还是相当强力的
In the older Cinebench R23,
更老的Cinebench R23当中
the 388H’s efficiency improvement is also obvious,
388H的能效进步同样明显
but the gap isn’t as large as in 2024.
不过差距没有2024里那么大
That’s mainly because R23 is less sensitive to memory,
这主要是因为R23对内存更不敏感
and focuses more on raw CPU performance.
更注重纯CPU的性能表现
And one huge highlight of the 388H comes from the memory subsystem upgrade.
而388H的一个巨大的亮点就是来源于内存系统的性能提升
Next, let’s look at another rendering test: Blender.
接着咱们继续来看另一个渲染性能测试Blender
The X9 388H has a small uplift over the previous 285H,
X9 388H比前代的285H有小幅提升
but is slightly behind HX370.
比HX370则要略弱一点
In the VS compile Dolphin test,
在VS编译Dolphin的测试当中
the X9 388H is also improved versus 285H,
X9 388H比起285H有一定的提升
and here the 388H is noticeably stronger than HX370.
在这里388H是比HX370明显强一些的
That result mainly comes down to stronger single-core and memory performance.
这个成绩主要还是依靠更强的单核和内存性能
Next up, 7-Zip compression and decompression.
接下来看看7Z压缩和解压性能
Because the memory controller is back in the right place,
由于内存控制器放回了正确的位置
the 388H makes some performance gains in 7-Zip compression,
388H在7z的压缩测试里有了一定的性能进步
though decompression is slightly weaker than HX370.
不过解压性能比HX370略弱一点
Overall, it’s a bit of give-and-take.
整体上算是此消彼长
In pure CPU performance tests,
纯CPU性能的测试里
this Ultra X9 388H’s performance level
这颗Ultra X9 388H的性能水平
is basically a small step up from the previous 285H.
基本上就是比前代285H小幅提升的水平
Compared with peak performance gains,
比起峰值性能的提升
the efficiency improvements this generation are more impressive.
这代处理器在能效上的提升更让人印象深刻
And that great efficiency isn’t just from the CPU;
而且这个优秀的能效表现不止来自于CPU
its GPU is even more eye-opening.
它的GPU更是令人刮目相看
In the 3DMark SNL efficiency test,
在3Dmark SNL能效测试当中
we also brought in the monster iGPU AI Max 395 for comparison.
我们加入了超大核显的AI Max 395来对比
As you know, the 395’s 8060s iGPU
你们也知道395的8060s核显
isn’t in the same class of specs as the other processors.
并不是和其他处理器类似规格的水平
It’s clearly larger and more expensive,
它明显更大也更贵
but it still works as a reference point
但我们依然可以用作参考系
to see just how strong the 388H’s GPU efficiency is.
来看看388H这颗GPU能效表现有多强
And it’s not hard to see that
不难发现啊
the 388H’s iGPU absolutely demolishes the previous 285H’s iGPU in efficiency.
388H这颗核显在能效上简直是吊打前代285H的核显
Even at just 15W it can easily beat the previous gen running flat out.
哪怕只有15W时都能轻松超过前代满血时的性能表现
It’s already close to double the performance of both 285H and HX370.
已经接近285H和HX370两倍的性能了
This 12Xe big iGPU’s performance really caught me off guard.
这颗12Xe的大核显表现实在是非常出乎我的意料
I knew it would be strong,
我知道它会很强
but I didn’t expect it to be this strong.
但也没想到会有这么强
Obviously, this is a big help for today’s thin-and-light iGPU laptops
很显然这对于目前的轻薄核显本
and even for handheld gaming PCs.
乃至于掌机的游戏表现都是非常有帮助的
Later we’ll also put this iGPU through real games
我们待会儿也会用实际游戏好好考验一下这颗核显
to see whether it’s a “high score, low real-world performance” kind of GPU.
看看它是不是一颗高分低能的GPU
Looking at peak performance,
从峰值性能来看
its SNL score is a major improvement over the previous iGPU.
SNL里面它的成绩比前代核显有显著的提升
So how does it compare with discrete GPUs?
那么它和独显对比又如何呢？
We specifically found two laptops with full-power 95W 3050 Ti
我们专门找了两台搭载满血95W 3050Ti
and a 130W 3060 as references.
和130W 3060的笔记本作为对比
You can see that in SNL, this iGPU scores almost exactly the same as a full-power 3050 Ti.
可以看到这个核显在SNL里成绩几乎和满血的3050Ti一模一样
We also tested its performance in Time Spy,
我们也测试了一下Time Spy里的表现
and here the 388H’s Arc B390 iGPU score is pretty crazy—
这里面388H这颗Arc B390核显分数就比较夸张了
well ahead of the 3050 Ti.
超过了3050Ti不少
But as you know, Intel iGPUs generally score unusually high in Time Spy,
但是你们也知道Intel的核显在Time Spy里的成绩普遍比较高
so from what I’ve seen, SNL is a more cross-platform-relevant benchmark.
我目前看下来还是SNL的测试成绩更具备跨平台的参考价值一些
After looking at the GPU’s 3DMark performance,
看完了GPU在3Dmark里的表现
we also tested its rendering performance in Blender.
我们还测试了一下它在Blender里的渲染性能
You can see it has evolved a lot compared to the previous gen,
可以看到它比前代也有相当大幅度的进化
almost matching the AI Max 395’s iGPU.
几乎和AI Max 395的核显持平了
And its score here is also about the same as the 3050 Ti.
它在这里的成绩和3050Ti也差不多
It seems the ray-tracing improvements across these two generations of Intel Xe graphics
看起来这两代Intel Xe显卡在光追上的提升
also pay off in Blender.
在Blender里也是很有收益的
In Photoshop, the 388H laptop lands between the 285H and HX370 models.
PS里388H的机型介于285H和HX370机型之间
In After Effects, it pulls noticeably ahead of both 285H and HX370.
AE里它则甩开了285H和HX370不小的距离
And in the more GPU-heavy Premiere, it extends its lead even further.
在更吃GPU的PR里进一步拉开了领先的幅度
It looks like Panther Lake’s 12Xe big iGPU
看起来Panther Lake这颗12Xe大核显
Paired with a more powerful codec.
配上更强的编解码器
It’s obviously very suitable for productivity uses like audio and video editing.
显然是非常适合这种音视频编辑的生产力用途
But if we’re talking about where the 12Xe iGPU really shines,
但要说12Xe核显真正的用武之地
then we have to look at its performance in games.
那必须还得来看看游戏里面的表现
Let’s start with Arknights: Endfield, which just went online recently.
咱们就从最近刚上线的《明日方舟：终末地》开始
Here we tested it at two quality presets.
这里我们跑了两档画质下的表现
First is 1080P at the very lowest settings.
首先是1080P极低特效下的表现
The X9 388H here even outperformed laptops with a 3060.
X9 388H在这里的表现甚至超过了3060的机型
That’s actually because the other two ran into a CPU bottleneck.
这其实是因为另外两者遭遇了CPU瓶颈
After all, the 11800H’s performance is a bit stretched thin today.
毕竟11800H的性能在今天还是有些捉襟见肘了
At 2K resolution, the results are more representative.
在2K分辨率下的表现则更有代表性一些
You can see the iGPU in the 388H is seriously capable.
你可以看到388H这颗核显是相当能打的
It’s 72% faster than the iGPU in the 285H.
直接比285H的核显强出了72%
That’s outrageous.
非常夸张
It also easily beats the 95W 3050 Ti.
这个表现也轻松干掉了95W的3050Ti
Only slightly behind the much larger 3060.
仅仅弱于规模大得多的3060
Next, let’s look at CS2.
接下来看看CS2里的表现
As an FPS online game that puts plenty of load on both CPU and GPU,
作为一个CPU和GPU压力都不小的fps网游
the 388H is about 50% faster than 285H machines at both resolutions.
388H在两档分辨率里都比285H的机型强出了50%左右
But the strongest here are still the 3060 and 3050 Ti.
不过这里最强的还是3060和3050 Ti
The HX370 also isn’t that far behind the 388H.
HX370的表现也没有被388H甩开太远
And pay attention to power draw.
而且注意看功耗
At this level of performance it’s only around 45W.
在这种性能下它居然只要45w左右的功耗
That means a thin-and-light with even modest cooling
这意味着稍微有点散热能力的轻薄本
can let this 388H deliver full-power gaming performance.
都可以让这颗388H拥有满血的游戏性能
That’s the craziest part.
这才是最夸张的
Next, let’s look at AAA games where the pressure is more concentrated on the GPU.
接下来来看看压力更集中在GPU部分的3A游戏
Starting with Black Myth: Wukong.
先从黑神话悟空开始
At 1080P without upscaling,
1080P不开超分的情况下
the 388H iGPU nearly doubles performance versus the 285H.
388H这颗核显几乎做到了相较于285H近乎翻倍的提升
It’s almost identical to a full-power 3050 Ti.
几乎和满血3050Ti表现一致
And it’s much faster than the HX370 too.
比HX370也强出许多
At 2K, turning on quality-mode upscaling like XeSS and DLSS,
进一步在2K分辨率下开启XeSS和DLSS等质量档超分
the 388H still goes toe-to-toe with the 3050 Ti.
388H依然可以和3050TI平起平坐
XeSS is also very close to DLSS in quality.
XeSS的效果也是很接近DLSS的水准
Image quality is clearly better than the FSR supported by the 890M iGPU.
画质明显比890M核显所支持的FSR强不少
Black Myth puts less load on the CPU,
黑神话的CPU压力要更低
so the SoC power draw during testing was lower too.
因此测试过程中的SoC功耗也来得更低
In most cases it was only 35–40W.
大部分情况下仅有35-40W的功耗水平
That efficiency is pretty astonishing.
这个能效表现相当惊人
Next up, the classic AAA title, Cyberpunk 2077.
接下来看看老牌3A，赛博朋克2077
Here, the 388H also achieved nearly double the performance compared with the 285H.
在这里388H同样获得了相较于285H几乎翻倍的性能
Whether at 1080P without upscaling or at 2K+ with quality-mode upscaling,
不论是1080P不开超分还是2K+质量档超分
this B390 iGPU performed extremely well.
这颗B390核显的表现都相当出色
Even at 2K with quality-mode XeSS,
甚至于2K质量档XeSS的时候
thanks to more flexible VRAM management,
凭借着更灵活的显存调度
it has already pulled ahead of the 3050 Ti with 4GB of VRAM.
它已经甩开了4G显存的3050Ti
It’s closer to 3060-level performance.
更接近3060的表现
In the TGA Game of the Year—Expedition 33,
TGA年度游戏——33号远征队里
the 388H also delivered close to a doubling in performance at both resolutions.
388H同样在两档分辨率下都获得了接近翻倍的性能提升
The 3050 Ti can still hang with the 388H at 1080P without upscaling.
3050Ti在1080P分辨率不开超分时还能和388H处在一个段位
But once you turn on upscaling at 2K,
一旦打开2K分辨率的超分
4GB of VRAM immediately becomes a limitation.
4GB显存立马就会捉襟见肘
So the 388H is able to overtake the 95W 3050 Ti.
388H也因此得以反超95W的3050Ti
The same situation continues in Kingdom Come: Deliverance II.
天国拯救2里同样延续了这样的情况
The 388H’s B390 iGPU,
388H的B390核显
whether at native 1080P
不管是在1080P原生分辨率下
or at 2K with quality-mode upscaling, performs very well.
还是2K质量档超分下表现都相当出色
It can also deliver nearly double the performance of the 285H.
同样可以获得近乎翻倍于285H的性能表现
The gaming experience it can provide
它能提供的游戏体验
is clearly worlds apart from traditional iGPUs like the HX370 and 285H.
显然和HX370、285H之类的传统核显有了天壤之别
After testing several games,
几个游戏测下来
Ultra X9 388H’s gaming performance left a deep impression on me.
Ultra X9 388H的游戏表现给我留下了深刻的印象
This new 12Xe iGPU’s performance in real games
这颗12Xe的新核显在实际游戏里的表现
is as stunning as its performance in 3DMark SNL.
和它在3Dmark SNL里的表现一样惊艳
Compared to absolute performance,
比起绝对性能
what’s more surprising is its efficiency in games.
更让人惊讶的是它在游戏里的能效表现
Basically, in games its power draw is around 30–50W.
基本上在游戏里它的功耗也就在30-50W之间
That’s not much different from the previous-gen 285H.
这和上一代的285H差别是不大的
That means if a 14-inch laptop has about 65W of cooling capacity,
这意味着如果有一台14寸笔记本拥有65W左右的解热能力
it’s enough to unleash almost all of the 388H’s potential.
就足够发挥这颗388H几乎全部的潜力了
In other words,
换句话说
an iGPU laptop with the 388H
搭载388H的核显笔记本
can absolutely achieve nearly full, uncompromised gaming performance on battery.
是完全有可能在离电情况下获得几乎完全不打折扣的游戏性能的
That’s something dGPU laptops are almost incapable of doing.
这才是独显笔记本几乎没有可能做到的事情
Take this Lenovo Xiaoxin Pro 16 GT AI (Yuanqi Edition) we have on hand as an example.
就拿我们手上的这台联想小新Pro 16 GT AI元启版为例
I specifically tested the frame rates in CS2 and Black Myth on battery.
我专门测试了一下CS2和黑神话离电情况下的帧数表现
You can see the performance loss is very slight.
你可以看到这个性能损失是非常轻微的
And this is only on the launch BIOS.
这还只是首发BIOS下的表现
After further tuning in future BIOS versions,
未来版本的BIOS进一步调教之后
I have every reason to believe laptops with Panther Lake
我完全有理由相信搭载Panther Lake的笔记本
can achieve exactly the same gaming performance on battery and on AC power.
有能力在离电和插电的情况下获得完全相同的游戏性能
At this point in the testing,
测试进行到这里
I believe you already have your own take on the performance of the Panther Lake architecture
我相信你已经对Panther Lake架构的
Core Ultra X9 388H.
酷睿Ultra X9 388H的性能表现有了自己的看法
In my view, this generation’s 12Xe is excellent,
在我看来这代12Xe版本的表现是非常优秀的
especially its efficiency, which left a very deep impression on me.
尤其是能效表现给我留下了非常深刻的印象
Whether it’s the CPU or the GPU,
不管是CPU还是GPU
You can see that this generation’s direction of evolution is
你可以看到这代的进化方向都是
moving toward lower power consumption and higher performance.
朝着更低功耗、更强性能的方向进行的
That makes me very curious:
那这就让我非常好奇
will this generation’s battery life also see a clear improvement?
这代处理器的续航表现会不会也有明显的进步
In the end, this Lenovo Xiaoxin Pro 16 GT AI Yuanqi Edition we have, at 120 Hz,
最终我们手上的这台联想小新Pro 16 GT AI元启版在120Hz刷新率下
ran for over 12 hours in our Geekerwan laptop battery-life model.
在我们的极客湾笔记本续航模型里跑出了12个小时多的续航成绩
Even considering the battery capacity increased by 19%,
即便考虑到电池容量增大了19%
reaching 99.9 Wh, the maximum you can take on a plane,
来到了能上飞机的最大容量99.9Wh
it’s still easy to see this generation made a clear leap in endurance.
也不难看出来这代处理器在续航上是有了明显进步的
We also tested battery life with the screen refresh rate set to 60 Hz.
我们还测试了一下这台机器在屏幕刷新率调整到60Hz时的续航成绩
It actually reached 14 and a half hours!
此时续航成绩居然来到了14个半小时！
No wonder it’s an SoC that inherits Lunar Lake’s design philosophy.
不愧是继承了Lunar Lake设计思路的SoC
I’d guess that this year, Windows iGPU laptops with Panther Lake
估计今年搭载Panther Lake的Windows核显本
should have no trouble hitting 10 hours of battery life.
续航成绩做到10个小时应该是一件相当轻松的事情了
After finishing this launch-day testing,
这次的首发测试做下来
Panther Lake’s performance left a deep impression on me.
这代Panther Lake的表现给我留下了深刻的印象
On the CPU side,
CPU部分
Intel 18A’s debut performance is excellent,
Intel 18A工艺首秀表现优秀
with efficiency even better than the 285H built on TSMC N3B.
能效比采用台积电N3B工艺的285H表现更上一层楼
It gives people hope that Intel’s process tech is back on track.
让人看到了Intel工艺又重新有了希望
On the GPU side, it gave us a big surprise:
GPU方面则给我们了一个大惊喜
whether it’s gaming, productivity, or efficiency,
不论是游戏性能、生产力性能还是能效表现
among the SoCs currently available in the Windows camp, it’s second to none.
在目前Windows阵营可选的SoC里都是无出其右的水平
This generation of Panther Lake is a laptop SoC that strongly prioritizes efficiency.
这代Panther Lake是一代相当注重能效表现的笔记本SoC
It even makes me a bit worried about Qualcomm’s X2 Elite, still not officially launched—
这让我甚至有点担心高通仍未正式推出的X2 Elite
what approach it will use to compete.
到底要用什么方式才能与之竞争
Now the only question is the pricing of Panther Lake models.
现在唯一的问题就是Panther Lake机型的价格了
The Lenovo Xiaoxin Pro 16 GT AI Yuanqi Edition we tested today
我们今天测试的这台联想小新Pro 16 GT AI元启版
will go on sale in China in March.
将于3月在国内上市
Something to look forward to.
可以期待一下
Let’s see what the pricing ends up being then.
看看到时候定价到底如何
Alright, that’s everything for our Panther Lake launch-day testing.
好了这次就是我们Panther Lake首发测试的全部内容了
If you like our show, don’t forget to long-press the Like button to support us.
喜欢我们的节目别忘了长按点赞键支持我们一下
And don’t forget to subscribe to our channel.
也千万别忘了关注我们频道
See you in the next episode.
下期节目再见吧